Nathanael Greene Papers 1777-1780 Mss.B.G83
American Philosophical Society
- Series I: Correspondence, 1777-1780; 3 lin. feet
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 6; 1p.; Wade, Francis (Box 6)
    Wilmington - Acknowledging favor of the 29th ult. Surprised at Col. Cox's omission to forward Gen. Greene his (Wade's) papers and returns, up to May 1. Just recovered from fit of sickness, but will set off the following day to the city and try to get copies of the returns. Badly off for a clerk who understands these matters, but will do the best he can.
    iii, 117
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 27; 2pp.; Wade, Francis (Box 6)
    Philadelphia - Acknowledging letter of 17th inst. Has sent the returns. Causes of the delay in his accounts: lack of money and proper assistants. Glad that time is arriving when a man may live in peace under his roof.
    iii, 118
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 18; 1p.; Wade, Francis (Box 6)
    Wilmington - Acknowledging favor of 9th inst. His efforts to get a clerk to help him with his books. Always considered his duty to his country rather than his private emolument. The many calls on him.
    iv, 119
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 2; 2pp.; Wade, Francis (Box 6)
    Philadelphia - Indignant at the late proceedings against the Staff department, which have failed again, according to the enclosed letter of Governor Rodney. Has assured the Governor that he will resume his station and continue his duties until a proper arrangement takes place. Want of cash. Flour at hand.
    viii, 100
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 28; 2pp.; Wade, Francis (Box 6)
    Wilmington - Acknowledging his favor of the 18th, also the books of certificates; the latter have caused a general alarm, preventing the people from coming in and settling their accounts; using every exertion to make the people take them. Unless money is provided, all supplies for the opening of the campaign will fall short. Lack of provisions for men and forage for horses at nearly all the posts that have been forwarding supplies for the army. For this reason has been obliged to let most of the teams withdraw from the service.
    iii, 61
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1778 November 25; 1p.; Wadsworth, Jeremiah (Box 6)
    Proclaiming his indifference to detraction or calumny. Not anxious to be classed with Gen. Greene's "wicked department." As he is dining at headquarters, will see him later.
    ii, 83
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 24; 3pp.; Wadsworth, Jeremiah (Box 6)
    Hartford - Body politic of Connecticut in a sad decay. Question of paying the bills at their nominal value. Not surprised at Gen. Sullivan's ordering a court of inquiry to investigate the conduct of the commissary for supplying his command. Is persuaded a more important inquiry will soon be necessary. Will avoid a quarrel if possible, but cannot promise.
    x, 7
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 7; 2pp.; Wadsworth, Jeremiah (Box 6)
    Hartford - Acknowledging favor of 30th ult. Will set out for camp soon, as he realizes he is needed there. Noise, confusion and dirt characterize this neighborhood; would rather be in Bedlam. Supply of cash to Hubbard saved their lives.
    vii, 16
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 28; 1p.; Wadsworth, Jeremiah (Box 6)
    Murderer's Creek - Letter from Bristol, R.I., which says the enemy have been blowing up and burning their works for two days, and all large ships have fallen down to the harbor's mouth. Enclosing certain letters.
    viii, 102
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 1; 1p.; Wadsworth, Jeremiah (Box 6)
    Murderer's Creek - Informing him of the sources form which he expects to draw great quantities of bread.
    ix, 120
  - to George Gray, 1778 December 26; 1p.; Walker (Box 6)
    Reminding him of his promise to give him the bedstead in the loft.
    xii, 87
  - to George Gray, 1778 December 30; 1p.; Walker (Box 6)
    xii, 95
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 30; 2pp.; War, Board of (Box 6)
    New Windsor - Acknowledging favor of 25th inst. Will use every exertion to forward the lead to Boston. If he had been informed of the business earlier, this crisis might have been avoided.
    vi, 104
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1778 October 29; 3pp.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Headquarters - Acknowledging favor of 28th inst. Nothing can be done toward the Canada expedition that winter; scanty supply of provisions afforded by the country at the head of Connecticut River. Will forbid the sending up of flour from Albany. Collecting and repairing of bateaux. Has fixed upon Danbury, West Point and Middlebrook for cantoning the army during the winter; number of brigades at these points to be regulated by the strength of the enemy. Probability of throwing a regiment into the Clove near Sufferans and placing a brigade at Albany. If the enemy keep a garrison at New York it will be of sufficient strength to repel any attack the Americans could make; would therefore lay aside all idea of collecting his force suddenly and extend his view to more remote cantonments. Good barracks at Trenton and Burlington; also wheat and mills in the vicinity. Advises removing provisions from the Sound to the foot of the mountain. Necessity of collecting materials for hutting.
    x, 40
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1778 December 17; 2pp.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Middlebrook - Enclosing copies of two letters - one to Mr. Wadworth concerning supplies for a large army to the northward, the other his answer, saying that the principal objection to the supplies being certain is the precariousness of carriage. Wants to know if it is possible for Gen. Greene to promise certain and uniform transportation.
    ii, 97
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 24; 2pp.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Headquarters, Middlebrook - Requesting him to consult with the Commissary-General about laying in a magazine of four month's provisions for 1200 men at Fort Pitt and for 100 men at Sunbury. Asking him also to obtain, in as secret a manner as possible, a list of all the vessels from the Falls of Susquehanna to Wyoming, and certain other details. Orders concerning the returns of each month. Preparations for an Indian expedition to be prosecuted agreeable to directions expected from Gen. Schuyler. No further action to be taken in providing materials for the vessels of force, but the articles already on hand are to be kept secure from waste and loss.
    ii, 95
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 March 2; 2pp.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    In the list submitted to him, if the articles are wholly designed for such troops as may proceed by way of Wyoming, thinks the quantity too great; but if they are part of the general provisions for the use of the army, they might as well be purchased on tolerably good terms.
    ii, 86
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 4; 1p.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Middlebrook - Having already explained the plan of the western expedition against the Indians of the Six Nations, now informs him that Gen. Sullivan is appointed to the command of the expedition, and desires that he will be ready, to enable him to make a general movement of the army. Gen. Greene knows the urgent motives to a speedy movement.
    vii, 28
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 6; 1p.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Headquarters, Middlebrook - The 1st New Jersey Regiment under marching orders, and will move probably in two days. Hears from Gen. Maxwell that their portmanteaux and wagons are lacking, and that the tents are not taken out of the store at Morristown for want of wagons. Gives him this notice that there may be no delay on the above account, the whole brigade being under marching orders.
    vii, 58
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 19; 1p.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Headquarters, Middlebrook - Enclosing a letter from Gen. Sullivan, with the several papers to which he refers. Difficulties arising from deficiency of wagons, tents, etc., in Gen. Greene's department will claim the earliest notice. Asking for Gen. Sullivan's letter and the return of the New Hampshire Regiment.
    v, 22
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 25; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Letter missing prior to 1990. No description in guide.
    vi, 9
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 31; 1p.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Headquarters - Acknowledging Gen. Greene's (?) favor, and happy to find the prospect of moving the army so good. Would wish to be in train to move by June 2.
    vi, 26
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 7; 1p.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Asking for a new order to prevent each regiment having so many wagons, and to keep women and lazy soldiers from riding in them.
    vi, 31
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 11; 1P.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Smith's Tavern - Desires the artificers will not be used in laying floors to tents; they are ended elsewhere, and also the floors will increase the baggage of the army, the officers being lot to leave them behind.
    vi, 50
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 5; 1p.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Headquarters, West Point - Requesting him to take every measure in his line to facilitate the junction of Gen. Sullivan's troops with this army.
    ii, 100
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 25; 2pp.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Headquarters - Requesting him to give the order to supply Mr. Hatfield with return wagons to carry 2000 dried hides to be sent to Philadelphia. Mentioning Gen. Sullivan's change of route and asking that an express may be sent to meet him.
    ii, 92
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 31; 1p.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Headquarters - Wishing to know if a sufficient number of vessels can be procured to transport troops up the river, should the Indian incursion to the northward prove serious.
    ii, 89
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 17; 2pp.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Headquarters, West Point - General directions for laying out the intended encampment. Position of brigades. Size and form of soldiers' barracks. Gen. Sullivan will furnish fatigue-men necessary for tracing the camp. Movement of baggage.
    ii, 90
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 23; 2pp.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Headquarters, West Point - Acknowledging favor of 22d. Question of choosing a winter position for the army. Disadvantages of the position below the mountain. Choice dependent on the number of the enemy's force and their possible movements.
    ii, 91
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 30; 1p.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Pompton - Acknowledging favor of he 27th. After a consideration of al circumstances has decided upon the position back of Mr. Kemble's, so that he may proceed to laying off the ground. Expects to be at Morristown the next day and will be obliged if Gen. Greene will order him a late dinner. Understands his quarters are to be at Mrs. Fords.
    ii, 84
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 December 23; 1p.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Headquarters, Morristown - Enclosing copy of letter received from Mr. Mitchell, showing how necessary his presence is in Philadelphia.
    ii, 93
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 2; 2pp.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Morristown - Acknowledging his letter of the day before. Concerning the dismission of express-riders; thinks as many as possible should be immediately discharged. Will write to Congress on the subject.
    ii, 101
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 24; 2pp.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Headquarters, Morristown - Concerning the dispossession of Capt. De. Rochefontaine of his quarters in favor of Lt. Col. Stevens. Unfortunate that such things should happen to any officers, but particularly to a foreign gentleman; wishes the affair rectified and put upon a proper footing. Has received Mr. Conduit's letter; Gen. Lee in that part of the country; trying to prevent the intercourse of which he speaks, but seems impracticable to put a stop to it.
    ii, 99
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 27; 1p.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Headquarters, Morristown - Orders to Gen. Greene to govern himself by the Act of 27th utl., directing the dismission of the express-riders, with certain exceptions.
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 30; 2pp.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Headquarters - Morristown - Advices received from Gen. St. Clair point tot he enemy's having some offensive operation in view. Therefore requests that he will use his best endeavors to remove the forage at or near the lines, to Morristown. Has sent a copy of letter representing state of his department to Congress.
    ii, 96
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 8; 1p.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Morristown - Acknowledging letter of same date, enclosing copy of one from Col. Berry, concerning the unwillingness of inhabitants to transport for the army at the regulated prices, from an apprehension that the regulations will not be general. Suggests the adoption of an expedient, it being indispensable that the transportation should go on with vigor.
    vii, 105
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 9; 2p.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Headquarters, Morristown - The enclosed (No. 104a) transmitted him by Board of War through Baron Steuben. Asks him to have the returns made out as soon as convenient.
    vii, 104
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 18; 1p.; Washington, George (Box 6)
    Headquarters, Morristown - Thinks it better that team with the clothing should not set out for Albany in the present state of the roads.
    ii, 98
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 25; 1p.; Wayne, Anthony (Box 6)
    Camp, Second River - Acknowledging his favor of that evening and promising to wait on him at nine o'clock in the morning, on condition that Gen. Greene will dine with him and spend the night.
    ii, 88
  - to George Gray, 1779 March 19; 1p.; Webb, Isaac (Box 6)
    Orders concerning a box being made to hold his linen.
    xii, 72
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1778 October 27; 1p.; Webb, Joseph (Box 6)
    By desire of Governor Trumbull is going to the lines with Governor Franklin. In receipt of countermand orders.
    viii, 107
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1778 November 9; 3pp.; Weedon, George (Box 6)
    Fredericksburg - Acknowledging letter of 14th ult., and congratulating him on the birth of a daughter. Would have given his only hat if it had been a son! Has leased a farm not to far from town, where his friends will always receive a hearty welcome, and if Mrs. Greene will come, promises her a ball every week. Great hopes at the beginning of the Rhode Island expedition, disappointed. Desires his opinion on the state of the arm, on the results of the Court-martial and the Eastern pole tax. Thinks the British are pretty tired and would gladly quit. Assembly still sitting; will communicate the heads of their deliberations in his next.
    ii, 102
  - to Robert Forsyth, 1779 February 2; 1p.; Weiss, Jacob (Box 6)
    Camp - Has just written to Col. Mitchell for leather. Will attend to stores.
    ix, 122
  - to Richard Claiborne, 1779 February 4; 1p.; Weiss, Jacob (Box 6)
    Camp - Giving names of persons in his department. Requests Col. Hay to send in the tents for repair.
    ix, 121
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 3; 1p.; Weiss, Jacob (Box 6)
    Ordering him to keep certain stores for the army and to forward others to Pluckemin, and then follow the army.
    vi, 14
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 10; 1p.; Weiss, Jacob (Box 6)
    Camp. Smith's Clove - Orders concerning the transportation of stores; let proper assortment come on at once to the army. Asks that an oil cloth he left behind may be forwarded.
    vi, 42
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 13; 1p.; Weiss, Jacob (Box 6)
    Smith's Tavern - Acknowledging letter of 9th inst. Tents for Gen. Sullivan wanted at once.
    vi, 60
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 10; 2pp.; Weiss, Jacob (Box 6)
    New Windsor - Enclosing Col. Mitchell's letter. Men actually suffering form want of blankets. Some coarse, blue woolens at the clothing store better than nothing. Wishes to know the General's opinion about issuing leather breeches to the artificers; also about getting returns of materials necessary for hutting, as the time for winter-quarters approaches.
    iii, 121
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 18; 1p.; Weiss, Jacob (Box 6)
    New Windsor - The bearer, Mr. New, waits on him with a desire of returning home to his family, his term of service being ended. Question of leather breeches.
    iii, 122
  - to George Olney, 1779 October 18; 1p.; Weiss, Jacob (Box 6)
    New Windsor - Wishing to borrow a small quantity of red ink; if the General is done with the books he left, would like them sent back by bearer.
    iii, 123
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 19; 2pp.; Weiss, Jacob (Box 6)
    New Windsor - Enclosing list of articles requisite for hutting the ten brigades. Suggestions for getting other returns for the same purpose.
    iii, 124
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 27; 1p.; Weiss, Jacob (Box 6)
    New Windsor - Concerning tents and returns.
    viii, 108
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 14; 1p.; Weiss, Jacob (Box 6)
    New Windsor - Will set off in the morning for Morristown. Asks that Mr. Tenbrook may be sent on before the army marches, to make certain preparations as regards to stores, hutting, etc.
    xii, 10
  - to George Olney, 1780 February 18; 1p.; Weiss, Jacob (Box 6)
    Enclosing account of certain clothing, and also of the prices estimated by Col. Mitchell, by which further settlements can be made.
    iii, 62
  - to George Olney, 1780 February 18; 2pp.; Weiss, Jacob (Box 6)
    Concerning shoes and the different prices at which they are selling; asks for some rule as a guide.
    ii, 103
  - to George Gray, 1779 April 9; 1p.; Welch, Nathaniel (Box 6)
    Order to repair one musket for the Second Virginia Regiment.
    xii, 97
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1778 October 21; 1p.; Wendell, Oliver (Box 6)
    Boston - Asking for an order on Gen. Heath for the sum mentioned in the account.
    x, 9
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 December 6; 1p. (Box 6)
    Greenwich - Sends by bearer, Adam Hawk, a saddle of venison; also some cereals for use of the forage department in Morristown.
    viii, 109
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 5; 1p. (Box 6)
    Greenwich - By request of Col. Hooper has purchased and sent on four turkeys, nine geese, and seven hens. Chairs will be ready some time the following morning.
    ii, 104
  - to Udny Hay, 1779 October 13; 3pp.; Whiting, Timothy (Box 6)
    West Point - His situation different from his brethren in office, on account of his being annexed to the line of the army; therefore ought to be treated on the same footing with a captain in the line, as was done in May, 1777. Has no aversion to the service, its hard work and inadequate pay, but thinks the sacrifice too great unless he has a prospect of being on a level with the officers of the line. Begs him to state the matter to the Quartermaster-General and request him to lay it before Congress, in which case he is willing to continue his services until January 1.
    iii, 59
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 8; 1p.; Whittelsey, Charles (Box 6)
    Providence - Directed by Gen. Gates to write the exact hour the express sets off with a letter from him to His Excellency, Gen. Washington. Col. Bowen has given orders to fix expresses at twenty miles distance from Providence, in accordance with orders received.
    iii, 119
  - to Udny Hay, 1779 October 8; 2pp.; Wickes, Thomas et. al. (Box 6)
    Fishkill - Concurring with the other officers in relation to their treatment by Congress, but differing with them (not through inclination, but had circumstances) respecting the time when they must resign; miserable situation of their families renders this precaution necessary.
    iii, 57
  - to unknown correspondent, 1779 October 10; 1p.; Wilkinson, James (Box 6)
    Muderer's Creek - Begs him to forward the enclosed to Mr. John Moylan, whose presence at Newbury to take charge of the magazine of clothing is immediately needed.
    ii, 105
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 27; 1p.; Williams, Oth. H. (Box 6)
    Found by inquiry that a certain Major-General can not be induced to accept employment on an expedition against the savages; shows not the least disposition for speculating in scalps.
    v, 81
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 3; 1p.; Williams, Oth. H. (Box 6)
    Morristown - Ordered by the Commander-in-Chief to furnish a battalion of between two and three hundred men to cover the stores and public offices in Morristown, and therefore applies to Gen. Greene for barracks or some other cover for them.
    ii, 106
  - to Charles Pettit, 1778 September 17; 1p.; Williamson, Matthias (Box 6)
    Elizabethtown - Asking for an inquiry into affair of one Capt. Riley, of the Twelfth Pennsylvania Regiment, who impressed a horse belonging to a Mr. Salter and never returned it.
    ix, 124
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 16; 1p.; Williamson, Matthias (Box 6)
    Elizabethtown - Introducing Mr. Aaron Woodruff, who has been an express-rider at the above post for three months, and if possible, desires his pay. If he is not paid, would like to know the amount of his wages and how the post is to be supplied with riders.
    iii, 64
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 18; 2pp.; Woodford, William (Box 6)
    Bound Brook - Complaining of Mr. Dunn's turning his horses into a small pasture already stocked with a sufficient number; knows Mr. Dunn could provide better pasture elsewhere, but he is piqued at being turned out of such comfortable quarters to give place to him (Woodford); asks that the matter be looked into.
    v, 23
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 25; 1p.; Woodford, William (Box 6)
    Haverstraw - Will begin his march for winter-quarters on the following day, but will have to stop two days at Suffern for the purpose of issuing clothing. Preparations he has made for the arrival of the troops.
    ii, 108
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 29; 1p.; Woodford, William (Box 6)
    Ramapo - Directed by His Excellency to ascertain where their huts are to be built, and if there is a nearer route than going round by Morristown. Has sent a detachment from each brigade, with their quartermaster, to Gen. Greene or one of his assistants for their proportion of tools.
    ii, 107
  - to the Armorer, n.d.; 1p.; Wodson, Hughs (Box 6)
    An order to repair the bear's musket.
    xii, 67
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 16; 1p.; Worthington, Asa (Box 6)
    Rariton - In want of more assistance in his work; asks for a certain artificers to help him for a few weeks.
    viii, 110
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 17; 2pp.; Worthington, Asa (Box 6)
    Rariton - Requested by Col. Wadsworth to order that the slaughter-house now begun in camp may be speedily completed. Gives his reasons for haste in this matter. Wishes a large vat made at the slaughter-house to salt the meat in as soon as it is killed.
    iv, 101
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 31; 3pp.; Young, Henry (Box 6)
    Lancaster - Delay of troops occasioned by want of horses. Movements of the Second Division. Apprehensive of further delays before reaching Fredericksburg, the road between that town and Leesburg being the worst on the continent. Wishes to know how the wagoners he has enlisted are to be supplied with clothes; also what is the pay of a wagonmaster. Promises returns of everything in the quartermaster's department. If he has to continue defraying his own expenses, will be ruined. Carelessness and villainy of wagoners.
    ii, 109
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 18; 3pp.; Young, Henry (Box 6)